<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Josh Martin</title>
    <description>Blog</description>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Your Inbox Just Got Dunked On</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I know, for a fact, I’m addicted to Dribbble — I check it before every project for inspiration and several times a day just to see what what is trending. For all intents and purposes, I do not need any other reminder of what is happening there. However, my friend and co-worker, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.andjosh.com&quot;&gt;Josh Beckman&lt;/a&gt;, does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sent that ungrateful bastard one of my Dribbble invites over a year ago an he has only posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/shots/1426532-Soundcloud-Logo-Animation?list=searches&amp;amp;offset=0&quot;&gt;one shot&lt;/a&gt;. His excuse(s)? “I just don’t have time to get on there… I forget it exists… It’s awful to look at on my small phone…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To thrust Mr. Beckman back into the game, we worked together to make &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;Alleyooop&lt;/a&gt;, a customizable newletter of Dribbble shots. You can adjust frequency of the newsletter and the type of shots you want to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, we only show the most popular shots (views + likes) from either Animated or nonanimated shots, but hope to allow even more filtration, such as location and by tag. We are currently wrestling with Dribbble’s API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the newsletter can be quite handy for not only Beckman, but other people too good or too busy (or too smart) to visit Dribbble regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;Give it a try!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/12/01/your-inbox-just-got-dunked-on</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/12/01/your-inbox-just-got-dunked-on</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bbbenched</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dribbble is my choice of social media for sharing my work. I love that it focuses on spontaneity and WIP, not necessarily polished, completed projects (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dribbble.com/2012/04/27/pro2.html&quot;&gt;Behance&lt;/a&gt;). With that being said, the platform is built for just that—quick uploads, small thumbnails, simple portfolios, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as time has passed, I use the platform less and less for sharing my own work and more for following professionals in my field that inspire me and collecting their work for future reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the only way to manage this list of followers and their work on Dribbble is by combing through your giant pools of ‘Likes’ and ‘Following’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who has used the platform for a few years, those pools are several hundred items full. To recall an artist or their work that I found a week ago can take 10+ minutes if I even find them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other route is a blind search of the entire website, hoping to the artist tagged their work appropriately and that the work got enough likes + views to be somewhere near the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, neither of these are very effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/bookmark-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How I currently manage my following list&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;How I currently manage my following list&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution I came up for this was creating an expansive list bookmarks in my browser, filled with links to artist Dribbble pages, and organized by skills and location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has worked for me and solved my biggest issue with Dribbble until Josh Beckman, suggested creating a similar functioning website that provided a tailored experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool we came up with was Bbbbench. It would be a bookmarking website in which you could take artists you follow and divide them up into unqiue groups for quick referencing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/homepage-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bbbench Homepage&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Bbbench Homepage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drag and Drop Interface for creating benches&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Drag and Drop Interface for creating benches&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/view-bench.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can view a bench by members or their artwork&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can view a bench by members or their artwork&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on Bbbench, off-and-on, for about 2 months. I would draw up the interfaces and UX, and Beckman would develop it. With the intention that the product could be very useful, I spent some extra time working on its branding, making a variety of illustrations and iconography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-3008-so-2000-and-late&quot;&gt;So 3008, So 2000 and late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late one night towards the end of the project, maybe a few days before pushing it live, I received a notification on Dribbble that said “User has added you to list.” I wasn’t quite sure what that meant, and low-and-behold, Dribbble implemented an organization feature that functioned exactly like Bbbench. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, they implemented it in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dribbble.com/2012/04/27/pro2.html&quot;&gt;April 2012&lt;/a&gt;, a whole &lt;em&gt;two years&lt;/em&gt; before we so brilliantly came up with the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/add.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can add members to a list through a dropdown&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can add members to a list through a dropdown&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/lists.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can view all of your created list in a separate section&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can view all of your created list in a separate section&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I most certainly think the feature was implemented poorly, that fact is that that the entire functionality of Bbbench already existed on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bbbench became pretty much useless and we stopped working on it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discussed with Beckman the possible pivot from web app to brower widget that could still make the quick referencing functionality of Bbbench still viable, but we have yet to take action on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project was fun nonetheless and a good exercise in creating a product from the ground up. It also gives perspective on the cutthroat startup culture where your next “big idea” is probably already being made by a dozen other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/03/01/bbbenched</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/03/01/bbbenched</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hummingbird Logo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My very talented friend and founder or Hummingbird, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joshfabian&quot;&gt;Josh Fabian&lt;/a&gt;, asked me to refresh its logo to coincide with a large website redesign. He felt his current version had a jagged silhouette and too fine of details that didn’t work at a small scale. A new logo was needed to reflect the website’s new direction and the bright future Hummingbird was working towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hummingbird&#39;s current logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&#39;s current logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For direction, Josh pointed me to Jord Riekwel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/shots/370581-Hummingbird&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&lt;/a&gt;, a logo he tried to purchase unsuccessfully prior to bringing me in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/jord.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jord Riekwel&#39;s Hummingbird logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Jord Riekwel&#39;s Hummingbird logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would characterize the desired icon as clean and minimal with sharp details; it is definitely strong enough to stand on its own, as well as be recognizable at any size. It’s relatively similar in style to what Josh had, but with a more simplified outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My job, more-or-less, was to find a middle-ground between the two.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Josh asked for an icon leaning closer in design to Riekwel’s, I wanted to make sure the direction I took was still unique, and most importantly different enough that the two marks could exist without stepping on each others’ wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started exploring ideas for the logo, I knew from the start that I wanted it to be bold and strong as, it alone, would need to be a symbol for an entire community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with lots of curves and sharp angles, cutting away at the overlapping sections where the tail and tail meet the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Early sketching&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Early sketching&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-exploration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proposed directions&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Proposed directions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After presenting a number of options, we ended up going with my second favorite direction (my first being a Japanese ‘Rising Sun’ inspired one) and it was probably the most straightforward merge of Jord’s logo and Josh’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the general shape of Jord’s and accentuated the wings and feathers with details similar to what Josh originally had, as well as elongating and contorting it’s body to suggest movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also put an emphasis on making the curves and angles exaggerated to give it the stronger look I was aiming for. I made its beak thick for better readability at smaller sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finalized Hummingbird logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Finalized Hummingbird logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’m very happy with how the logo turned out. I knew when taking on the project that I was walking a fine line in terms of how similar Josh wanted the logo to be to Jord’s, but I’m confident that we came up with a unique treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an artist, (for at least me anyways) I stake claim to anything I do or make as 100% mine — I came up with the perfect idea all on my own, with no one’s help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, unfortunately, that’s rarely the case. You take little bits here and an idea there, and rearrange them strategically until the end result is unique enough to call your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you do this willingly by visiting your favorite websites or projects for inspiration, or sometimes, as in this case and most, it’s straightup asked that you make something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel such a situation is normal and the process is acceptable as long as nothing is a flat-out copied. Everything you make needs to have more of your fingerprints on it than anyone else’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-wild&quot;&gt;In the wild&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo has really taken on a personality all its own since I handed it off. I’ve seen it on t-shirts, wallpapers, cover photos, avatars…everywhere in all sorts of variations. It’s pretty cool; I’m very glad the community has embraced it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/inthewild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hummingbird&#39;s logo with app icon treatment&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&#39;s logo with app icon treatment&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love anime or want to see the logo in its natural environment, head over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hummingbird.me&quot;&gt;www.hummingbird.me&lt;/a&gt; and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2013/08/01/hummingbird-logo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2013/08/01/hummingbird-logo</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Redesigning Power2Switch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/himlrsgz671oocb/graduate.jpg?dl=0&quot;&gt;graduated college&lt;/a&gt; and moved to Chicago in hopes that the big city could provide big job opportunities. After discovering my traditional graphic design and animation degree wasn’t quite lining up well-paying suitors, I started teaching myself web design and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward two months, and I would be neck deep in my first real job putting the new skills to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was brought into &lt;a href=&quot;https://power2switch.com&quot;&gt;Power2Switch&lt;/a&gt; after they sent an inquiry via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;1871&lt;/a&gt; to my friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joshfabian&quot;&gt;Josh Fabian&lt;/a&gt; (whom I was living with at the time and helping me learn web design/development). He graciously put in a good word for me, and days later, I was starting full-time as an intern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power2Switch&#39;s then-current homepage and rates/comparisons page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Power2Switch&#39;s then-current homepage and rates/comparisons page&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My responsibilities with Power2Switch varied a good bit: I was brought in primarily to focus on design and development, but I also worked on email campaigns, blog post illustrations, pitch decks, and copywriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the many projects I worked on, the redesign of the company’s website was, by far, the most important (and challenging). My responsibility was to create a better web experience for users and help educate them on the value of the the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we even formally began on the project, I enthusiastically started working on my own. I presented a coded, responsive redesign of Power2Switch’s then-current homepage and pitched my ideas for improving their online product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/initial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial direction for homepage redesign&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Initial direction for homepage redesign&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design was OK (at best), but clearly showed how limited my experience in web was— it was bloated, formulaic, completely disregarded branding, and didn’t adequately inform new users how Power2Switch worked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly learned that in order to be successful, I would need input from people with much more knowledge of the product than I had— POV’s from all sides of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I worked with an extremely talented group of people, each with a wealth of experience, that could help point me in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jakelumetta&quot;&gt;Jake Lumetta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lead Software Engineer&lt;/em&gt;,  made sure my designs translated well to code and gave me direction when they didn’t&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/suzelmoursi&quot;&gt;Suzanne EL-Moursi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Digital Strategy Mangager&lt;/em&gt;, made sure my designs maintained the brand’s voice (and stayed clear from terrible stock photos!)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/js_powerplay&quot;&gt;J.S. Roy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Director of Engineering and Operations&lt;/em&gt;, taught me how the product worked and why it’s valuable, so I can better communicate it to users&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jamailcarter&quot;&gt;Jamail Carter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Director of Business Development&lt;/em&gt;, made sure I was targeting the right audience and how to capitalize my designs for them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/seyi_fab&quot;&gt;Seyi Fabode&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/plnevels&quot;&gt;Philip Nevels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CEO’s and Founders&lt;/em&gt;, kept me motivated, challenged me, and encouraged me to take chances&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my only experience as a designer a that point was working in print, navigating the limitations and goals of the web became an everyday learning-experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In print, the goal is to communicate a message. Plain and simple. You are concerned with presenting said message in a way that is, above all else, clear and understandable to the desired reader and hopefully envokes an emotional response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your only limitations are your imagination and printing costs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything thing else boils down to a combination of design fundamentals and subjectivity, taste: color, typography, texture, imagery, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/wireframe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Notes and early wireframes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Notes and early wireframes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in web is a whole other beast entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to constantly be aware of multitude of constantly changing factors: Users (age, intelligence, habits, experience, etc.), Branding (tone, colors, style), ads, content, navigation, development (responsiveness, speed, compatibility)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It becomes very similar to solving a puzzle that changes the size and number of pieces every time you turn your back.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In working on Power2Switch’s website, I was way past simply trying to communicate a message as I did in print— I was guiding them to the message, giving them a reason to read it, teaching them how to read it, and convincing them act on what it says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was constantly taking psychological approaches to everything I was doing, trying to put myself in their shoes, and imagining how I would react/engage with every element on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, this project definitely became the foundation of my career in user-interface and user-experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, before joining Power2Switch, I neither cared or was even remotely interested in where my electricity comes from or even if I was paying too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most, when it comes to electricity (or any other utility), I simply Google electricity + my zipcode and choose the first one. I was really surprised to find not only are there multiple options, but electricity or utilites compete against each other are like any other businesses, offering competitive rates and differing types of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting this concept across to potential Power2Switch customers was absolutely essential.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to informing potential customers that they have a choice in who provides their electricity, I also had to find a way to inform them how exactly Power2Switch was involved the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/how.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The How-It-Works page is one of Power2Switch&#39;s most visited&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The How-It-Works page is one of Power2Switch&#39;s most visited&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a typical shopping website, such as Amazon, Power2Switch aggregates all of the possible suppliers into one platform and let users pick the one that best suits their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the user doesn’t already have a supplier, Power2Switch sets its up for them. If they do, Power2Switch handles the transition from their current provider to the new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the page, I made illustrations and wrote copy that I felt best got this information across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homepage&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my initial proposal for the homepage, the page was very long: It composed of a hero image, a list of “how it works” sections, “As seen in” highlights, and a CTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in-all, it was pretty bloated. Going in a second time, the goal was to simplify and to concentrate the bulk information to the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suzanne EL-Moursi, our Digital Strategy Manager, ingrained in me the need for &lt;em&gt;obvious over clever&lt;/em&gt;— put everything immediately in front of them and give them the clearest possible path to the CTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result was a straightforward headline, a step-by-step overview of how it works, and an input for the user’s zip code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/homepage-all.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new Power2Switch homepage got rid of everything beneath &#39;the fold&#39;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The new Power2Switch homepage got rid of everything beneath &#39;the fold&#39;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;onboarding&quot;&gt;Onboarding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more interesting aspects of the project was the idea of improving conversion—what can we do get more users to go through the entire checkout process? Or rather, what have we been doing that hasn’t been effective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on Power2Switch’s analytics, there was a huge drop off on the the comparisons page, which where users can see all suppliers available, based on their zipcode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/onboarding.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The user answers a few questions before seeing possible suppliers&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The user answers a few questions before seeing possible suppliers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the homepage was bringing potential customers in, but they were quitting and leaving the site before selecting a supplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was concluded the reason for this was users were being overwhelmed by the amount of choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution I proposed was an onboarding page or “wizard set-up” to better direct users to their ideal supplier. With a few basic questions, they could reduce their results from a dozen, down to only a handful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rates-and-comparison&quot;&gt;Rates and Comparison&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When presenting the available energy providers, I had to get across a great deal of information, such as energy rating, price, energy source, and plan duration, in a simple, efficient, and unintimidating way, as well as give user the ability to sort through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My strategy was to use fundamental design principals, such straightforward iconography and appropriately varying sizes, weights, and colors of typography to highlight key information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made sure interactive elements, such as sorting buttons, and links, such as the “make the switch” CTA, we unobstructed and easy to locate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/rates.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Viewing Bench&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Viewing Bench&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to listing the available options, the page also has left rail of support and guides to help users understand the information they are being presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From discussions with support, many customers found that the pricing (fixed vs nonfixed) and savings calculations we hard to understand. Many didn’t even know what KWh (kilowatt hour) meant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aliviate this, I worked with J.S. Roy, the Director of Engineering and Operations, to help come with the appropriate copy to explain it all, including explainations of fixed cost, and pricing trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a conscious decison to show the content upfront instead of redirecting users to other pages or hiding it in a modal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;personal-information-and-legal&quot;&gt;Personal information and Legal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step in the checkout process is a two-parter: entering personal information (service address, utility details) and reviewing the terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/info.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users enter information needed for Power2Switch to complete their enrollment or switch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users enter information needed for Power2Switch to complete their enrollment or switch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/legal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Terms and Conditions were simplified for better comprehension&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The Terms and Conditions were simplified for better comprehension&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, both pages are pretty straightforward and changed very little from their previous design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did, however, try to improve the readability of Terms and Conditions page: I organized it into small easily-digestible bullet points, listing out exactly how the process will go down and what they are agreeing to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-to-development&quot;&gt;Moving to Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the designs in place, the next step would be turning them all into HTML and CSS and delivering them to our backend developer, Jake Lumetta. At the time, I was unfamiliar with Git and delivered them, hilariously, through email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even funnier, was my inability to grasp cross-browser compatibility. Jake and I would constantly go back and forth to make edits when pushed into production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/closeup-rates.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The rates comparisons page was the most difficult to code&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The rates comparisons page was the most difficult to code&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who had only two months of self-taught web development under his belt, the process was full of learning experiences and, of them, two that stood out were: learning how to make a responsive dropdown menu on mobile and learning how to make CSS sprites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lights-turned-off&quot;&gt;Lights turned off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the development process, Power2Switch began to engage in talks to be acquired by their Texas-based rival, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chooseenergy.com/&quot;&gt;Choose Energy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I gathered, Power2Switch felt the move was best because it would allow for them to move into a more commercial energy space and deal with larger companies, which were far more lucrative than residential space they had made a name in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously put the entire team’s focus on the acquisition and moved redesign to the furthest possible backburner. We eventually got to launching the homepage, but the rest were never implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/homepage-tablet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The homepage redesign was the only page pushed live&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The homepage redesign was the only page pushed live&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is unfortunate because we never got to see what the new design could have done— whether it could have substantially improved conversion, engagement, or excitement in the brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquision process took quite some time and during all of it, money was scarse. Many employees stayed on to work without pay, some took second jobs, and others, like myself, left to find other forms of employment until it all shook out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, the acquisition process took several months (about 7) to &lt;a href=&quot;http://tech.co/choose-energy-acquires-techstars-alum-power2switch-2013-10&quot;&gt;complete&lt;/a&gt;, and by that time, I had already moved on to new job opportunities in freelance, as well as a new full-time job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my coworkers, such as Jake and Suzanne, continued on to join Choose Energy, while others went on to take on new jobs, start personal projects, or be with their family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/legal-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power2Switch Terms and Conditions&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Power2Switch Terms and Conditions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I would have loved to see the redesign implemented, as I though it could have been successful, it all worked out for the best: Power2Switch continues to grow and improve the quaility of their service; they have expanded Choose Energy’s reach even further throughout the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands now, the Power2Switch website operates as extension/affiliate, redirecting visitors to Choose Energy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2013/04/01/redesigning-power2switch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2013/04/01/redesigning-power2switch</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>