<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hank Quinlan, Horrible Cop</title>
    <description></description>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Afterskoolz Case-Study</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2014, I was approached by my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aggrego.com&quot;&gt;Aggrego&lt;/a&gt; co-worker, &lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/sal-abbasi&quot;&gt;Sal Abassi&lt;/a&gt;, to help get his personal project, Afterskoolz, off the ground. It would be a platform to make finding and planning after-school activites for children easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sal, alongside fellow parent and Afterskoolz co-founder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/mustafa-patni&quot;&gt;Mustafa Patni&lt;/a&gt;, laid out a rough draft of all the features they wanted Afterskoolz to have, such as simple search functionality, class registration, teacher-to-parent messaging, and a schedule-overlayed calendar. With their vision laid out, it was my job to bring it to life through comprehensive UI/UX design and branding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Early planning and wireframing&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Early planning and wireframing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;planningresearch&quot;&gt;Planning/Research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sal and Mustafa explored their possible competition well before bringing me onboard, discovering the space for innovation was huge— Not a single platform for finding after-school activities will show up in a Google Search for “After-school activities for kids.” You will only see listicles/articles on suggested activity ideas, a few local businesses, and unhelpful government-created programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sal and Mustafa concluded that only competition in after-school class discovery was a small San Francisco-based startup, called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kidfully.com&quot;&gt;Kidfully&lt;/a&gt;; Kidfully focuses on the social aspect of reviewing and sharing after-school activities with fellow parents in the SF area; this is a direction similar, but not the same for what was in mind for Afterskoolz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/google.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;No discovery platform will show up in Google Search&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;No discovery platform will show up in Google Search&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterskoolz would be less about recommendations and building a social community like sites such as Kidfully or Angie’s List, and more about shopping for classes and registering for them— making it more similar to traditional shopping sites, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; or even &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.grubhub.com&quot;&gt;Grubhub&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 24yr old, single, recent college grad, the platform obviously doesn’t speak to me and my needs, but, it doesn’t take much to understand how such a platform could revolutionize what appears to be a stagnant industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterskoolz could, potentially, be the go-to destination for parents to browse a large selection of after-school activities in their city and easily, quickly get their children involved; it would completely rid the burden of tradtional paperwork and phone calls, making the process as simple as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kidfully, Wyzant, Treehouse, and Amazon inspired Afterskoolz&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Kidfully, Wyzant, Treehouse, and Amazon inspired Afterskoolz&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s even more amazing, is the platform doesn’t have to stop at after-school activities: it could completely replace traditional class registration at every educational level. Take this scenario for example: You just moved to a new city and need to register your child into the new local school. What do you do? You call the school, schedule an appointment, gather identification materials, and physically go to said school to fill out paperwork…why should anyone have to do that in 2015?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the inital plan for Afterskoolz isn’t quite ready to tackle a terriotry like complete school registration, it is an important aspect to keep in mind for the future, especially as I build my blueprint for the website. I must keep everything I design agile and capable of scaling and accomodating new features/functionaility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;user-studies&quot;&gt;User-Studies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started to build the outline for Afterskools, it was very important, from a high-level, to understand exactly the type of users it was targeting and what features/functionalities they require. While the obvious goal is provide every feature these users could ever want, it is imporant to discern what is essential and what isn’t, especially when creating an MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;user-studies&quot;&gt;

  &lt;li class=&quot;user cf&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;box-left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;user-profile&quot;&gt;
        &lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/woman-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;box-right&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;1. Parents&lt;/h4&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The obvious target user is a Parent and we put priority on features they would need above all else, save for administrators. One of the last functionilites we added, surprisingly, was mobile capability. Initally, Sal and Mustafa wanted Afterskoolz to be desktop-only, but changed course after getting feedback from other parents. We also discussed dedicated apps, but decided to hold off due to limited development resources.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;       
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Search for local classes for their kids&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Register for classes online&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Blog/ideas/suggestions for new classes&lt;/span&gt;        
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Manage accounts for multiple children&lt;/span&gt;        
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Message teachers&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Google Calendar Integration&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Mobile functionality&lt;/span&gt;      
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Dedicated iOS/Android app&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Carpooling/Child pick-up&lt;/span&gt;  
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Google Map Integration&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Share/Endorse Classes&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class=&quot;user cf&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;box-left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;user-profile&quot;&gt;
        &lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/woman-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;box-right&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;2. Principals&lt;/h4&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ideally, Afterskoolz would love for Principals to leave their local paperwork-based systems and instead manage every aspect of their school, such student registration, finances, etc, on their platform. However, such a system would require a lot more work and lot of dedication that would take away from developing for other equally-valuable users. The comporomise was easing in the functionality, such as simple roster management, a little bit at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Manage their school&#39;s account information&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Add/Remove teachers&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Add/Remove students&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Add/Remove classes&lt;/span&gt;        
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Manage student records/paperwork&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Manage financials/payments&lt;/span&gt;    
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Review/approve new class endorsements&lt;/span&gt;  
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Google Spreadsheet importing/editing/exporting&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class=&quot;user cf&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;box-left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;user-profile&quot;&gt;
        &lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/woman-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;box-right&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;3. Teachers&lt;/h4&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Probably the least amount of attention was given to functionality for Teachers&amp;mdash;they can only message parents and principals. Eventually, we would like to facilitate contact between them and their students, such as the ability to post assignments on dedicated class page.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Message Parents&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Message Principals&lt;/span&gt;        
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Message Students&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Add/Remove students&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Keep track of attendence&lt;/span&gt;  
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Manage grades&lt;/span&gt;                
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Dedicated class page&lt;/span&gt;            
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;LiveChat-style teaching sessions&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Pinned documents, messages, posts for students&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;check&quot;&gt;Send documents/assignments&lt;/span&gt;                  
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class=&quot;user cf&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;box-left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;user-profile&quot;&gt;
        &lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/woman-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;box-right&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;4. Administrators&lt;/h4&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In general, administrators need functionaility to view, approve, add, and edit all data on Afterskoolz, especially in the event a Principal/school is not actively managing their account. This would prove to be one of the more complex obstacles for the project. Because of the quantity and variety of data they would be handling, a simple &quot;Fill out this form to add a school, class, etc.&quot; would not suffice. We needed the ability to scrape entire websites/webpages for multiple schools, classes, etc and fill out multiple forms at the same time. Also, viewing all of this information one page at time would be impossible, so spreadsheet integration was also a necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Message all users&lt;/span&gt;          
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Review/approve new school claims&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Review/approve class suggestions&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Deactive/remove/add users&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Create/remove class categories&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Manually scrape URLs&lt;/span&gt;  
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Custom scrape URLs&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;checkmark&quot;&gt;Google Spreadsheet importing/editing/exporting&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding Afterskoolz functionality for children, such as the ability to talk with their classmates and teachers for children was discussed, but shelved in favor of focusing on other users. The idea of social-networking capabilities is obviously worthwhile and, I’d imagine, will be added sooner, rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;site-map&quot;&gt;Site Map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easiest to understand the Afterskoolz platform by looking at it from a bird’s eye view; it is extremely multifunctional: It acts as a public-facing discovery tool, a e-commerce platform, a private organization service, a communication interface, and a management aid. All of these functions differ in one way or another from user-to-user. It can get quite confusing if it is not planned and organized properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/site-map-basic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A basic blueprint to show exactly how it is all connected&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;A basic blueprint to show exactly how it is all connected&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wireframes&quot;&gt;Wireframes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After determining how the site is organized and what pages are needed, I define the website’s front-facing visuals. I establish layout, page content, user-interface elements. I also double-check the site’s UX as I work page-to-page. It’s pretty easy to change course or make significant revisions at this step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of wireframes isn’t to focus on the final product, but to illustrate, at the most basic level, the functionality or purpose of each page. Elements such color and branding are, no doubt, an important part of any website, but they don’t (or shouldn’t, at least) affect how a page/website will work. In my experience, at least, adding these superfluous details only causes distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/wireframe-detailed-desktop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;High-fidelity wireframes convey proposed design direction for Desktop&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;High-fidelity wireframes convey proposed design direction for Desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/wireframe-detailed-mobile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;High-fidelity wireframes convey proposed design direction for Mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;High-fidelity wireframes convey proposed design direction for Mobile&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;presentation-testing-and-prototyping&quot;&gt;Presentation, Testing, and Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the site map laid out and the wireframes completed, the next step is to finalize the direction before moving to mockups. I do this in two steps: a static prototype and an interactive prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/site-map-detailed-desktop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Connecting desktop wireframes via sitemap&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Connecting desktop wireframes via sitemap&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/site-map-detailed-mobile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Connecting mobile wireframes via sitemap&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Connecting mobile wireframes via sitemap&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staic prototype is a .PDF of all the high-fidelity wireframes laid out like the sitemap and the interactive prototype is that same static prototype, but tangible and better replicating a real-life product. I need both of these prototypes not only for myself, but for the people that handling my work when I’m not around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The static mockup puts into words exactly how each page works and what will or should happen when it is interacted with; this is an invaluable reference to developers as the prototype moves from prototype to code. While I think clients can appreciate seeing this, too, in my experience, they tend to get overwhelmed. (The various “if this/then that” scenarios are enough to make most peoples’ eyes to gloss over)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clients, on the other hand, tend to react more positively to actually interacting with the product you are making for them. I find that they can more easily point out things that they like, dislike, or have suggestions for improving this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/prototype.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It&#39;s easy to spot UX flaws when using prototypes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;It&#39;s easy to spot UX flaws when using prototypes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides being a better way for clients to test their potential product, interactive prototyping is also invaulable for testing my designs on multiple devices. Platforms such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.invisionapp.com&quot;&gt;Invison&lt;/a&gt; allow you to view your your design on wide-range of mobile and tablet devices in addition to desktop. It’s extremely helpful to make sure everthing I initially design on a laptop, does in fact, look how I want it at various sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;branding-and-logo&quot;&gt;Branding and Logo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to my involvement in the web design process, I also worked heaviliy in branding. Sal and Mustafa came to me with the “Afterskoolz” name and some general direction: they wanted it to be “fun and friendly,” emphasize color, and, in no way, be confused with a corporate business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored several ideas and eventually chose to base the branding off of a chalkboard motif as it pertains to classrooms and students. I liked the idea of scribbled headlines and doodle-style illustrations. I also felt that the dark blue of a chalkboard would work well with a very expansive color palette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The logo was inspired by Toys R&#39; Us, Google, Oreo, and ebay&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The logo was inspired by Toys R&#39; Us, Google, Oreo, and ebay&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Afterskoolz logo, I chose a large, slab-serif typeface, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fontsquirrel.com/fonts/chunkfive&quot;&gt;Chunkfive&lt;/a&gt;, that I felt was playful. I combined it with an another classroom motif, the teacher’s apple. I felt a stylized version of it compliment the wordmark well and could still be strong on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/business-card.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Businesses cards with embossed details&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Businesses cards with embossed details&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;style-guide&quot;&gt;Style Guide&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the branding in order, I translated it into a style guide for the website. I wanted to establish a consistent visual style for color, typography, illustrations, iconograpy, and UI elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/style-guide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A detailed style guide is very helpful when handing design off to developers&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;A detailed style guide is very helpful when handing design off to developers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homepage&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homepage, like in most projects, tends to draw the most input from clients; they usually have a pretty clear vision for how they want to present their product and the atmosphere they want to create for prospective visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this, the back-and-forth between myself and the client tends to take far longer than any other aspect of the website’s UI. In designing the Afterskoolz homepage, the main areas of concern from Sal and Mustafa was picking a powerful (yet friendly) hero image, a very direct search CTA, and a fun way to list the available classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/homepage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The relatively-simple homepage design responds down nicely to tablet and mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The relatively-simple homepage design responds down nicely to tablet and mobile&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of solving for their main concerns, I wanted to make sure the homepage got the Afterskoolz branding across in a tasteful, subtle manner— personable, informal copywriting, delightful animations, spot illustrations, and playful iconography. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as layout, it’s pretty standard in modern design practices for homepages to be: Hero image, product selling points, website section highlights, and CTA. I followed this formula pretty closely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;search-results&quot;&gt;Search Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search-results page, in my opinion, is the most important page of the entire site; you want it to convey a large amount of information in a simple, unintimidating way. At the same time, you want to give users the ability to access a large varitey of additional details and search customization if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/search-results.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sal and Mustafa stressed the importance of a map and save-class buttons in the page&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Sal and Mustafa stressed the importance of a map and save-class buttons in the page&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;class-profile&quot;&gt;Class Profile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class profile page is divided into 3 sections: details, endorsements, and schedule. The Details section elaborates on information showed initially in the search results, the Endorsements section showcases administrator-selected class recommendations (NOT Yelp-style reviews), and the schedule section presents all available sessions for enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/class-profile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The schedule section overlays a registered user&#39;s Google Calendar for easy referencing&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The schedule section overlays a registered user&#39;s Google Calendar for easy referencing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dashboard&quot;&gt;Dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve stated before, Afterskoolz isn’t just about discovery and registration— it has a wide assortment of tools and functionality, each tailored for its four types of users. For example, parents need the ability to manage their children’s schedules, teachers need to send homework to students, principals need to manage rosters, and administrators need to collect/view school data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/dashboard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/messaging.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Messaging is feature available to all users&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Messaging is feature available to all users&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;development&quot;&gt;Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of a project, you inherently become better and smarter; you tend to find your mistakes from the first month and the second month and so on. However, it is impossible to move forward if you keep looking back. One of the hardest things to do is say: “Hey, this isn’t perfect. There’s a lot of things I’d like to change now that I know better, but we’ll cross that bridge later.” The main thing is delivering a solid product so it can be developed and launched quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, after about four months of working on Afterskoolz, there is definitely areas I would like to revist and improve. Specifically, I’d like to improve main/sub navigation, redesign search results page, expand branding color palette, and add stronger illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/homepage-future.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Messaging is feature available to all users&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Messaging is feature available to all users&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/search-results-future.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Messaging is feature available to all users&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Messaging is feature available to all users&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2015-03-01-afterskoolz-case-study/email-future.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Messaging is feature available to all users&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Messaging is feature available to all users&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have a lot of things I’d like to improve about Afterskoolz, I am, overall, very proud of the product I helped build; I believe it has bright future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the moment I am writing this case-study, my work is being handed over to developers with the hope that an Afterskoolz MVP (limited to Chicago-only) will be launched Summer 2015.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/03/01/afterskoolz-case-study</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/03/01/afterskoolz-case-study</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Your Inbox Just Got Dunked On</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I know, for a fact, I’m addicted to Dribbble — I check it before every project for inspiration and several times a day just to see what what is trending. For all intents and purposes, I do not need any other reminder of what is happening there. However, my friend and co-worker, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.andjosh.com&quot;&gt;Josh Beckman&lt;/a&gt;, does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sent that ungrateful bastard one of my Dribbble invites over a year ago an he has only posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/shots/1426532-Soundcloud-Logo-Animation?list=searches&amp;amp;offset=0&quot;&gt;one shot&lt;/a&gt;. His excuse(s)? “I just don’t have time to get on there… I forget it exists… It’s awful to look at on my small phone…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To thrust Mr. Beckman back into the game, we worked together to make &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;Alleyooop&lt;/a&gt;, a customizable newletter of Dribbble shots. You can adjust frequency of the newsletter and the type of shots you want to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, we only show the most popular shots (views + likes) from either Animated or nonanimated shots, but hope to allow even more filtration, such as location and by tag. We are currently wrestling with Dribbble’s API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the newsletter can be quite handy for not only Beckman, but other people too good or too busy (or too smart) to visit Dribbble regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;Give it a try!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/12/01/your-inbox-just-got-dunked-on</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/12/01/your-inbox-just-got-dunked-on</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The World Revolves Around the Sun</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The last project I did with Aggrego is most certainly the largest, and for me, up until that momement, the most significant of my career. I was given the opportunity to redesign the Chicago Sun-Times and extend the brand across websites and apps in 70 of the largest cities in the US as part of the “Sun-Times Network.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggrego, the company I was technically employed by for this project, is generally a software development startup that creates and manages news media networks. It employees a extremely talented mix of developers and engineers who build the networks from the ground up, and content creators who fill said networks with highly-monetizable content. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aggrego Tech Team working on Sun-Times Network&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Aggrego Tech Team working on Sun-Times Network&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my tenure with Aggrego, we worked on a wide range of inhouse projects, such as Weekaway and Rankommend, but focused primarily on building for others. A few of our client projects include managing Sun-Times Media Group’s Chicago suburb news network, Pioneer Press, building Digicel’s international news network, Loop, and testing Communicorp’s multi-county Ireland news network, Today.ie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Sun-Times Network&lt;/strong&gt; would be another of these client projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was proposed by Sun-Times Media Group’s owner, Wrapports, LLC, as a one-off extention of the Chicago Sun-Times brand into Milwaukee, WI. However, as we started mapping out the product it started to be apparent that the process for “Milwaukee Sun-Times” could be duplicated infinitely, assuming we could create a scalable template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial Pitch work for Milwaukee Sun-Times&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Initial Pitch work for Milwaukee Sun-Times&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;board-meetings-on-board-meetings-on-board-meetings&quot;&gt;Board Meetings on Board Meetings on Board Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun-Times Network was my first experience working in real corporate environment. I would spend my entire time on the project working alongside many established news industry figures such Wrapports chairman, Michael Ferro, Wrapports CEO Timothy Knight, Wrapports EVP of Marketing, Julian Posada, and Aggrego CEO, Tim Landon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that being said, my contributions to planning/researching for Sun-Times Network began and ended with the direction given to me by this group. As the lead designer of this project, I proposed solutions and ideas, but ultimately, it was my job to carry out their vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Sun-Times Network wanted to distance itself from it diminishing reputation.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The Sun-Times Network wanted to distance itself from it diminishing reputation.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up front, the general conscensus was that the product needed to be “younger”, “hipper”, “trendier”, and a host of other buzz words. More-or-less, they wanted the product to be the &lt;strong&gt;exact opposite&lt;/strong&gt; of the current Chicago Sun-Times. With that being said, comparisions to Twitter and Buzzfeed were tossed around frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggregate content
Built on Social
Emphasis on apps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gaol was to create a platform that could engaging content that is extremely shareable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, in a project this scale and working with so many high-level voices, my input, for better-or-for-worse was taken with a grain of salt. Personally/Professionally, I would have put more emphasis catering functionaility, features, to Chicago Sun-Times’s established user-base to better acclimated them to the new platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that is my opinion, I do not necessarily think out approach to completely pivot in a new direction was a bad decision. Instead of a “hold your hand” approach, we were able to build a platform with having to compromise any of the project’s main goals, whch was first-and-foremost, build a dynamic, brand new platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-need-a-logo-for-this-thing-and-you-got-4-hours&quot;&gt;We Need a Logo for This Thing (and you got 4 hours)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branding Sun-Times was entirely my own endevor. Surprisingly, very little direction was given in branding the new Sun-Times. I distictly rememeber Aggrego CEO, Tim Landon telling me “Just do something the complete opposite of the current Sun-Times. The only restriction is you can’t use red. Michael Ferro hates red.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-month-sprint-launching-mvp&quot;&gt;Two-Month Sprint, Launching MVP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branding Sun-Times was entirely my own endevor. Surprisingly, very little direction was given in branding the new Sun-Times. I distictly rememeber Aggrego CEO, Tim Landon telling me “Just do something the complete opposite of the current Sun-Times. The only restriction is you can’t use red. Michael Ferro hates red.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sun-times-20&quot;&gt;Sun-Times 2.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branding Sun-Times was entirely my own endevor. Surprisingly, very little direction was given in branding the new Sun-Times. I distictly rememeber Aggrego CEO, Tim Landon telling me “Just do something the complete opposite of the current Sun-Times. The only restriction is you can’t use red. Michael Ferro hates red.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/mood-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;USA Today, New York Post, and Boston.com inspired Sun-Times Network&#39;s design&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that being said, I explored a few idea and eventuall settled on a dark color scheme. The idea was that it could both convey a sense of seriousness, and boldness. It also allowed for an expansive color pallette. I was looking for something that would be appropriate for serious and pop culture stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-wont-believe-what-happens-next&quot;&gt;You Won’t Believe What Happens Next!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first joined Aggrego, the company identified itself as a startup. The general atmosphere was exciting as we seemed to be moving project-to-project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as we progressed with the Sun-Times Network, it became increasingly apparent what the priorities were and it was to create an amazing, game-changing product. While I’ve learned the monetization is iand pleasing those who have the money is extremely important, I didn’t feel comfortable producing a product I would never use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/homepage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire project became “How many pageviews?” and “Where can we stick a banner ad?”. This was literally the only things talked about. Product Design was an extremely low-priority as my contributions became more about “Photoshopping” graphics and ideas that product managers and sales couldn’t do themselves. The level of innovation was as low as you could imagine. It became “copy what they did over there and put our logo on it”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I obviously upset with the direction Sun-Times took, that is not to say I wasn’t proud of my contributions and the wonderful people I worked with in the trenches. We built an amazing product very, very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to move on from Aggrego following the completion of Sun-Times Network V.2. While I was extremely happy with what I accomplished, I learned that the digital news media game wasn’t for me. I didn’t take pleasure in the type of content we were producing, or the advertisements we were covering our website in. I also learned that the corporate environment wasn’t for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my final two weeks with Aggrego, I prepped the gameplan for Sun-Times V.3, focusing on improving the article page and homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/homepage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-12-01-the-world-revolves-around-the-sun/article.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users have all of their tools and information readily available in their dashboards&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to move on from Aggrego following the completion of Sun-Times Network V.2. While I was extremely happy with what I accomplished, I learned that the digital news media game wasn’t for me. I didn’t take pleasure in the type of content we were producing, or the advertisements we were covering our website in. I also learned that the corporate environment wasn’t for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of January, 2015, the proposed changes were not implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/12/01/the-world-revolves-around-the-sun</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/12/01/the-world-revolves-around-the-sun</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bbbenched</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dribbble is my choice of social media for sharing my work. I love that it focuses on spontaneity and WIP, not necessarily polished, completed projects (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dribbble.com/2012/04/27/pro2.html&quot;&gt;Behance&lt;/a&gt;). With that being said, the platform is built for just that—quick uploads, small thumbnails, simple portfolios, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as time has passed, I use the platform less and less for sharing my own work and more for following professionals in my field that inspire me and collecting their work for future reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the only way to manage this list of followers and their work on Dribbble is by combing through your giant pools of ‘Likes’ and ‘Following’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who has used the platform for a few years, those pools are several hundred items full. To recall an artist or their work that I found a week ago can take 10+ minutes if I even find them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other route is a blind search of the entire website, hoping to the artist tagged their work appropriately and that the work got enough likes + views to be somewhere near the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, neither of these are very effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/bookmark-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;How I currently manage my following list&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;How I currently manage my following list&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution I came up for this was creating an expansive list bookmarks in my browser, filled with links to artist Dribbble pages, and organized by skills and location. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has worked for me and solved my biggest issue with Dribbble until Josh Beckman, suggested creating a similar functioning website that provided a tailored experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool we came up with was Bbbbench. It would be a bookmarking website in which you could take artists you follow and divide them up into unqiue groups for quick referencing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/homepage-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bbbench Homepage&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Bbbench Homepage&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drag and Drop Interface for creating benches&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Drag and Drop Interface for creating benches&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/view-bench.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can view a bench by members or their artwork&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can view a bench by members or their artwork&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on Bbbench, off-and-on, for about 2 months. I would draw up the interfaces and UX, and Beckman would develop it. With the intention that the product could be very useful, I spent some extra time working on its branding, making a variety of illustrations and iconography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-3008-so-2000-and-late&quot;&gt;So 3008, So 2000 and late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late one night towards the end of the project, maybe a few days before pushing it live, I received a notification on Dribbble that said “User has added you to list.” I wasn’t quite sure what that meant, and low-and-behold, Dribbble implemented an organization feature that functioned exactly like Bbbench. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, they implemented it in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dribbble.com/2012/04/27/pro2.html&quot;&gt;April 2012&lt;/a&gt;, a whole &lt;em&gt;two years&lt;/em&gt; before we so brilliantly came up with the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/add.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can add members to a list through a dropdown&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can add members to a list through a dropdown&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2014-03-01-bbbenched/lists.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can view all of your created list in a separate section&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;You can view all of your created list in a separate section&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I most certainly think the feature was implemented poorly, that fact is that that the entire functionality of Bbbench already existed on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bbbench became pretty much useless and we stopped working on it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discussed with Beckman the possible pivot from web app to brower widget that could still make the quick referencing functionality of Bbbench still viable, but we have yet to take action on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project was fun nonetheless and a good exercise in creating a product from the ground up. It also gives perspective on the cutthroat startup culture where your next “big idea” is probably already being made by a dozen other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/03/01/bbbenched</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/03/01/bbbenched</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hummingbird Logo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My very talented friend and founder or Hummingbird, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joshfabian&quot;&gt;Josh Fabian&lt;/a&gt;, asked me to refresh its logo to coincide with a large website redesign. He felt his current version had a jagged silhouette and too fine of details that didn’t work at a small scale. A new logo was needed to reflect the website’s new direction and the bright future Hummingbird was working towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hummingbird&#39;s current logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&#39;s current logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For direction, Josh pointed me to Jord Riekwel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/shots/370581-Hummingbird&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&lt;/a&gt;, a logo he tried to purchase unsuccessfully prior to bringing me in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/jord.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jord Riekwel&#39;s Hummingbird logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Jord Riekwel&#39;s Hummingbird logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would characterize the desired icon as clean and minimal with sharp details; it is definitely strong enough to stand on its own, as well as be recognizable at any size. It’s relatively similar in style to what Josh had, but with a more simplified outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My job, more-or-less, was to find a middle-ground between the two.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Josh asked for an icon leaning closer in design to Riekwel’s, I wanted to make sure the direction I took was still unique, and most importantly different enough that the two marks could exist without stepping on each others’ wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started exploring ideas for the logo, I knew from the start that I wanted it to be bold and strong as, it alone, would need to be a symbol for an entire community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with lots of curves and sharp angles, cutting away at the overlapping sections where the tail and tail meet the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Early sketching&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Early sketching&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-exploration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Proposed directions&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Proposed directions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After presenting a number of options, we ended up going with my second favorite direction (my first being a Japanese ‘Rising Sun’ inspired one) and it was probably the most straightforward merge of Jord’s logo and Josh’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the general shape of Jord’s and accentuated the wings and feathers with details similar to what Josh originally had, as well as elongating and contorting it’s body to suggest movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also put an emphasis on making the curves and angles exaggerated to give it the stronger look I was aiming for. I made its beak thick for better readability at smaller sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/hummingbird-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finalized Hummingbird logo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Finalized Hummingbird logo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’m very happy with how the logo turned out. I knew when taking on the project that I was walking a fine line in terms of how similar Josh wanted the logo to be to Jord’s, but I’m confident that we came up with a unique treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an artist, (for at least me anyways) I stake claim to anything I do or make as 100% mine — I came up with the perfect idea all on my own, with no one’s help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, unfortunately, that’s rarely the case. You take little bits here and an idea there, and rearrange them strategically until the end result is unique enough to call your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you do this willingly by visiting your favorite websites or projects for inspiration, or sometimes, as in this case and most, it’s straightup asked that you make something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel such a situation is normal and the process is acceptable as long as nothing is a flat-out copied. Everything you make needs to have more of your fingerprints on it than anyone else’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-wild&quot;&gt;In the wild&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo has really taken on a personality all its own since I handed it off. I’ve seen it on t-shirts, wallpapers, cover photos, avatars…everywhere in all sorts of variations. It’s pretty cool; I’m very glad the community has embraced it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-08-01-hummingbird-logo/inthewild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hummingbird&#39;s logo with app icon treatment&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&#39;s logo with app icon treatment&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love anime or want to see the logo in its natural environment, head over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hummingbird.me&quot;&gt;www.hummingbird.me&lt;/a&gt; and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2013/08/01/hummingbird-logo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2013/08/01/hummingbird-logo</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Redesigning Power2Switch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/himlrsgz671oocb/graduate.jpg?dl=0&quot;&gt;graduated college&lt;/a&gt; and moved to Chicago in hopes that the big city could provide big job opportunities. After discovering my traditional graphic design and animation degree wasn’t quite lining up well-paying suitors, I started teaching myself web design and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward two months, and I would be neck deep in my first real job putting the new skills to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was brought into &lt;a href=&quot;https://power2switch.com&quot;&gt;Power2Switch&lt;/a&gt; after they sent an inquiry via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alleyooop.info&quot;&gt;1871&lt;/a&gt; to my friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joshfabian&quot;&gt;Josh Fabian&lt;/a&gt; (whom I was living with at the time and helping me learn web design/development). He graciously put in a good word for me, and days later, I was starting full-time as an intern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power2Switch&#39;s then-current homepage and rates/comparisons page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Power2Switch&#39;s then-current homepage and rates/comparisons page&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My responsibilities with Power2Switch varied a good bit: I was brought in primarily to focus on design and development, but I also worked on email campaigns, blog post illustrations, pitch decks, and copywriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the many projects I worked on, the redesign of the company’s website was, by far, the most important (and challenging). My responsibility was to create a better web experience for users and help educate them on the value of the the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we even formally began on the project, I enthusiastically started working on my own. I presented a coded, responsive redesign of Power2Switch’s then-current homepage and pitched my ideas for improving their online product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/initial-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial direction for homepage redesign&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Initial direction for homepage redesign&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design was OK (at best), but clearly showed how limited my experience in web was— it was bloated, formulaic, completely disregarded branding, and didn’t adequately inform new users how Power2Switch worked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly learned that in order to be successful, I would need input from people with much more knowledge of the product than I had— POV’s from all sides of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I worked with an extremely talented group of people, each with a wealth of experience, that could help point me in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jakelumetta&quot;&gt;Jake Lumetta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lead Software Engineer&lt;/em&gt;,  made sure my designs translated well to code and gave me direction when they didn’t&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/suzelmoursi&quot;&gt;Suzanne EL-Moursi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Digital Strategy Mangager&lt;/em&gt;, made sure my designs maintained the brand’s voice (and stayed clear from terrible stock photos!)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/js_powerplay&quot;&gt;J.S. Roy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Director of Engineering and Operations&lt;/em&gt;, taught me how the product worked and why it’s valuable, so I can better communicate it to users&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jamailcarter&quot;&gt;Jamail Carter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Director of Business Development&lt;/em&gt;, made sure I was targeting the right audience and how to capitalize my designs for them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/seyi_fab&quot;&gt;Seyi Fabode&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/plnevels&quot;&gt;Philip Nevels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CEO’s and Founders&lt;/em&gt;, kept me motivated, challenged me, and encouraged me to take chances&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my only experience as a designer a that point was working in print, navigating the limitations and goals of the web became an everyday learning-experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In print, the goal is to communicate a message. Plain and simple. You are concerned with presenting said message in a way that is, above all else, clear and understandable to the desired reader and hopefully envokes an emotional response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your only limitations are your imagination and printing costs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything thing else boils down to a combination of design fundamentals and subjectivity, taste: color, typography, texture, imagery, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/wireframe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Notes and early wireframes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Notes and early wireframes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in web is a whole other beast entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to constantly be aware of multitude of constantly changing factors: Users (age, intelligence, habits, experience, etc.), Branding (tone, colors, style), ads, content, navigation, development (responsiveness, speed, compatibility)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It becomes very similar to solving a puzzle that changes the size and number of pieces every time you turn your back.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In working on Power2Switch’s website, I was way past simply trying to communicate a message as I did in print— I was guiding them to the message, giving them a reason to read it, teaching them how to read it, and convincing them act on what it says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was constantly taking psychological approaches to everything I was doing, trying to put myself in their shoes, and imagining how I would react/engage with every element on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, this project definitely became the foundation of my career in user-interface and user-experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, before joining Power2Switch, I neither cared or was even remotely interested in where my electricity comes from or even if I was paying too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most, when it comes to electricity (or any other utility), I simply Google electricity + my zipcode and choose the first one. I was really surprised to find not only are there multiple options, but electricity or utilites compete against each other are like any other businesses, offering competitive rates and differing types of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting this concept across to potential Power2Switch customers was absolutely essential.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to informing potential customers that they have a choice in who provides their electricity, I also had to find a way to inform them how exactly Power2Switch was involved the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/how.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The How-It-Works page is one of Power2Switch&#39;s most visited&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The How-It-Works page is one of Power2Switch&#39;s most visited&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a typical shopping website, such as Amazon, Power2Switch aggregates all of the possible suppliers into one platform and let users pick the one that best suits their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the user doesn’t already have a supplier, Power2Switch sets its up for them. If they do, Power2Switch handles the transition from their current provider to the new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the page, I made illustrations and wrote copy that I felt best got this information across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homepage&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my initial proposal for the homepage, the page was very long: It composed of a hero image, a list of “how it works” sections, “As seen in” highlights, and a CTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in-all, it was pretty bloated. Going in a second time, the goal was to simplify and to concentrate the bulk information to the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suzanne EL-Moursi, our Digital Strategy Manager, ingrained in me the need for &lt;em&gt;obvious over clever&lt;/em&gt;— put everything immediately in front of them and give them the clearest possible path to the CTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result was a straightforward headline, a step-by-step overview of how it works, and an input for the user’s zip code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/homepage-all.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new Power2Switch homepage got rid of everything beneath &#39;the fold&#39;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The new Power2Switch homepage got rid of everything beneath &#39;the fold&#39;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;onboarding&quot;&gt;Onboarding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more interesting aspects of the project was the idea of improving conversion—what can we do get more users to go through the entire checkout process? Or rather, what have we been doing that hasn’t been effective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on Power2Switch’s analytics, there was a huge drop off on the the comparisons page, which where users can see all suppliers available, based on their zipcode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/onboarding.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The user answers a few questions before seeing possible suppliers&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The user answers a few questions before seeing possible suppliers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the homepage was bringing potential customers in, but they were quitting and leaving the site before selecting a supplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was concluded the reason for this was users were being overwhelmed by the amount of choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution I proposed was an onboarding page or “wizard set-up” to better direct users to their ideal supplier. With a few basic questions, they could reduce their results from a dozen, down to only a handful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rates-and-comparison&quot;&gt;Rates and Comparison&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When presenting the available energy providers, I had to get across a great deal of information, such as energy rating, price, energy source, and plan duration, in a simple, efficient, and unintimidating way, as well as give user the ability to sort through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My strategy was to use fundamental design principals, such straightforward iconography and appropriately varying sizes, weights, and colors of typography to highlight key information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made sure interactive elements, such as sorting buttons, and links, such as the “make the switch” CTA, we unobstructed and easy to locate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/rates.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Viewing Bench&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Viewing Bench&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to listing the available options, the page also has left rail of support and guides to help users understand the information they are being presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From discussions with support, many customers found that the pricing (fixed vs nonfixed) and savings calculations we hard to understand. Many didn’t even know what KWh (kilowatt hour) meant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aliviate this, I worked with J.S. Roy, the Director of Engineering and Operations, to help come with the appropriate copy to explain it all, including explainations of fixed cost, and pricing trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a conscious decison to show the content upfront instead of redirecting users to other pages or hiding it in a modal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;personal-information-and-legal&quot;&gt;Personal information and Legal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step in the checkout process is a two-parter: entering personal information (service address, utility details) and reviewing the terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/info.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Users enter information needed for Power2Switch to complete their enrollment or switch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Users enter information needed for Power2Switch to complete their enrollment or switch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/legal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Terms and Conditions were simplified for better comprehension&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The Terms and Conditions were simplified for better comprehension&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, both pages are pretty straightforward and changed very little from their previous design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did, however, try to improve the readability of Terms and Conditions page: I organized it into small easily-digestible bullet points, listing out exactly how the process will go down and what they are agreeing to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-to-development&quot;&gt;Moving to Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the designs in place, the next step would be turning them all into HTML and CSS and delivering them to our backend developer, Jake Lumetta. At the time, I was unfamiliar with Git and delivered them, hilariously, through email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even funnier, was my inability to grasp cross-browser compatibility. Jake and I would constantly go back and forth to make edits when pushed into production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/closeup-rates.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The rates comparisons page was the most difficult to code&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The rates comparisons page was the most difficult to code&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who had only two months of self-taught web development under his belt, the process was full of learning experiences and, of them, two that stood out were: learning how to make a responsive dropdown menu on mobile and learning how to make CSS sprites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lights-turned-off&quot;&gt;Lights turned off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the development process, Power2Switch began to engage in talks to be acquired by their Texas-based rival, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chooseenergy.com/&quot;&gt;Choose Energy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I gathered, Power2Switch felt the move was best because it would allow for them to move into a more commercial energy space and deal with larger companies, which were far more lucrative than residential space they had made a name in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously put the entire team’s focus on the acquisition and moved redesign to the furthest possible backburner. We eventually got to launching the homepage, but the rest were never implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/homepage-tablet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The homepage redesign was the only page pushed live&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The homepage redesign was the only page pushed live&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is unfortunate because we never got to see what the new design could have done— whether it could have substantially improved conversion, engagement, or excitement in the brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquision process took quite some time and during all of it, money was scarse. Many employees stayed on to work without pay, some took second jobs, and others, like myself, left to find other forms of employment until it all shook out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, the acquisition process took several months (about 7) to &lt;a href=&quot;http://tech.co/choose-energy-acquires-techstars-alum-power2switch-2013-10&quot;&gt;complete&lt;/a&gt;, and by that time, I had already moved on to new job opportunities in freelance, as well as a new full-time job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my coworkers, such as Jake and Suzanne, continued on to join Choose Energy, while others went on to take on new jobs, start personal projects, or be with their family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;text-left block cf image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post/2013-04-01-redesigning-power2switch/legal-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power2Switch Terms and Conditions&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;text-small&quot; align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Power2Switch Terms and Conditions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I would have loved to see the redesign implemented, as I though it could have been successful, it all worked out for the best: Power2Switch continues to grow and improve the quaility of their service; they have expanded Choose Energy’s reach even further throughout the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands now, the Power2Switch website operates as extension/affiliate, redirecting visitors to Choose Energy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2013/04/01/redesigning-power2switch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2013/04/01/redesigning-power2switch</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>